<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the cathedral church of Worcester upon the monthly fast-day, September 16. 1691 by William Talbot ...</title>
            <author>Talbot, William, 1658 or 9-1730.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62583</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T122</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33893</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13598713</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13598713</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100734</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62583)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100734)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1051:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the cathedral church of Worcester upon the monthly fast-day, September 16. 1691 by William Talbot ...</title>
                  <author>Talbot, William, 1658 or 9-1730.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Bennet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Amos IV, 21 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100734:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100734:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the Cathedral Church OF WORCESTER UPON THE <hi>
                  <hi>Monthly Faſt-Day,</hi> September</hi> 16. 1691.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM TALBOT,</hi> D.D. and DEAN of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed at the Requeſt of the MAYOR and ALDERMEN of that City.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Bennet</hi> at the Half-Moon in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:100734:2"/>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:100734:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON ON AMOS iv. 21. <hi>Therefore thus will I do unto thee, O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I will do this unto thee, prepare to meet thy God, O</hi> Iſrael.</head>
            <p>THE Occaſion and Deſign of the appointment of this days Faſt having been at large declared in the Royal Edict ſet forth for that purpoſe, and after ſo many monthly returns of it, are, I ſuppoſe, ſo well known that it will not be neceſſary for me to ſpend much time in opening them to you.</p>
            <p>Only thus much give me leave to obſerve by way of Preface, that we are at this time neceſſarily engaged in a very great Undertaking, upon the ſucceſs of which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends the ſafety and eſtabliſhment of all that can be dear to us as Men, <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> or Proteſtants, the ſecurity of our Lives and Liberties, of our Civil Rights and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, and, which I hope we hold dearer than all, our Reformed Church and Religion.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:100734:3"/>
            <p> The Enemies who from Abroad (and O that they were all, that we had none at Home joyning with them in carrying on the ſame Black Deſign;) the Enemies, I ſay, that are contriving and labouring the ruin of all theſe; are furniſhed with all thoſe Qualities and Proviſions that can make an Adverſary either Odious or Formidable, to be abhorred or feared; Baſeneſs, Treachery, Cruelty, Numbers, Wealth, Policy. The Head of them is one who breaths nothing but Blood, Fire, and Devaſtation; whoſe only glory is to make Orphans and Widows, to lay Countries Waſte, and Cities in Aſhes, and tinge their Rivers with innocent Gore; whoſe barbarity to thoſe of the Reformed Religion, who hold the Faith as it is in Jeſus, and was by him delivered to the Saints, is ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſidented, that the Perſecuting, whether Heathen or Arrian, Emperours were comparatively Nurſing Fathers of the Chriſtian and Orthodox Church; whoſe regard to the Sacred Ties of Promiſe or Oath are ſo ſmall, that he ſeldom gives either with any other deſign than to make advantage by breaking them: in a word, whoſe Injuſtice, Tyranny, Cruelty and Perfidiouſnes have juſtly rendered him the common Nuſance, as well as Peſt of Mankind. The whole Body of them are ſuch as are obliged by all the ties that a pretended Infallible Church, or cunning Prieſts, can lay upon their credulous Proſelites, that are muffled up in an Implicit Faith, and blind Obedience to their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Guides, by all methods, how Barbarous and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian ſoever (the end will Sanctifie the Means) to Extirpate us Hereticks, as they are pleaſed to call us: a piece of whoſe Religion it is to ruin us, and who think that by Murdering us they do God, as well as their Church, good Service. A War, with ſuch Enemies, has given occaſion to this days Faſt.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100734:3"/>
            <p> The deſign of which, is not that we ſhould only im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon our ſelves the eaſie Pennance of a few hours Abſtinence from the refreſhments of our Tables; ſpend two or three in our attendance upon the Publick Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, or a day in fruitleſs Lamentations and Complaints; but that we ſhould ſeriouſly, and in good earneſt, ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a ſtrict and impartial examination of our ſelves, ſearch out by what ſins we have been affronting and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking our God, and conſequently ſerving our Enemies, and contributing to our own Ruin: That we ſhould Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tently acknowledg, humble our ſelves for, and reſolve againſt them for the future; that we ſhould put on Holy Purpoſes, enter into ſtrict Obligations of new Obedience to our God, of purſuing thoſe Means whereby we may engage Heaven to come into an Alliance with us, that we ſhould endeavour to Know and Practice in this our Day the things that belong unto our Peace, before they be hid from our Eyes; in ſhort, that we ſhould exerciſe an unfeigned and Univerſal Repentance, and engage in a thorough and general Reformation:</p>
            <p>For the furthering of which great and pious Deſign, The words which I have now Read, will give occaſion to ſome Meditations, that may prove, I hope, not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unſerviceable. <hi>Therefore thus will I do unto thee O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and becauſe I will,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The firſt word the illative Particle, <hi>Therefore,</hi> ſhews us that the Verſe is a Concluſion grounded upon ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that went before, and for our more clear and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitable Underſtanding of it ſends us back to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:100734:4"/>
            <p> From the 6th. Verſe we find God, by the Prophet, enumerating ſeveral Judgments that he had exerciſed them with, and yet complaining that for all that they had not returned unto him, ſuch as Famine, Verſes 6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>I have given you cleaneſs of teeth in all cities, and want of bread in all your palaces,</hi> &amp;c. Such as Peſtilence and Sword, Verſe 10. <hi>I have ſent among you the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence after the manner of</hi> Egypt, <hi>your young men have I ſlain with the ſword, and made the ſtink of your camp to come up into your noſtrils,</hi> &amp;c. Fire and devaſtation, Verſe 11. <hi>I have overthrown ſome of you as God overthrew</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Gomorrah, &amp;c. but ſtill the burden of all is, <hi>Yet have ye not returned unto me,</hi> and then follows in the words of the Text, <hi>Therefore thus will I do unto thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, (i. e.)</hi> Becauſe ye have defeated the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns and Ends of my Judgments, have reſiſted the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Efforts of thoſe Diſpenſations which were intended for your Admendment, and to have brought you Home unto my Self, becauſe ye have not been Reformed by them, but continue incorrigible under them: <hi>Therefore, Thus will I do unto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is ſome little difference among Commentators con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Meaning of this Phraſe; ſome think that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to thoſe Judgments which he had before ſpoken of, as if the meaning of <hi>I will do thus unto thee,</hi> was, I will again in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict the ſame Judgments upon you, the Famine, Peſtilence, Fire and Sword, which you have already ſmarted under.</p>
            <p>But I rather conceive with others, that here is a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure in the words, commonly known to Rhetoricians by the name of <hi>Apoſiopeſis,</hi> by which a perſon that is in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or threatens ſpeaks ſhort, and ſuppreſſes part of the Sentence, as if his Paſſion would not give him leave to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100734:4"/>ſpeak out all that he meant: Thus <hi>Neptune</hi> in <hi>Virgil,</hi> when he was wroth with and chid the Winds, cryes only, <hi>Quos Ego</hi> — whom I — meaning, whom I will beſure ſeverely to chaſtiſe: So in Sacred Writ we read often this Expreſſion, God do ſo unto me, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> let him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict the ſevereſt of his Curſes upon me: And it is no new thing for God in Scripture to ſpeak after the manner of Men, and for the Holy Spirit, although they are moſt abhorrent from his Nature, yet in condeſcention to our Capacities, to attribute Paſſions, as well as Parts to him; and therefore I apprehend there is that Figure here, <hi>I will do thus unto thee, i. e.</hi> I will inflict Judgments upon thee which I have conceived in my angry mind, but are too big to be worded. <hi>And becauſe I will do thus unto thee,</hi> becauſe thou haſt provoked me to come out in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and great fury againſt thee, <hi>Prepare to meet thy God, O</hi> Iſrael. This Clauſe is likewiſe capable of a double Conſtruction, and may either be taken for a biting Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſm, as if the great God ſpoke to them in deriſion, as he threatens his wretched obſtinate Enemies in the firſt of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> that he will laugh at their Calamity, and mock when their Fear comes, as if he did deridingly Challenge them to come forth and Combat with him, bid them Arm themſelves with all the defenſatives they could provide, and try if they could make their parts good with him.</p>
            <p>Or elſe it may be Underſtood in another Senſe, as a Kind and Compaſſionate Exhortation to them to come and meet him in a way of Penitence and Supplication, that ſo they might appeaſe his Anger, and reverſe the terrible Decree that was gone forth againſt them: as if, according to the Parable, he bid them ſit down and conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were able with ten thouſand to meet him that came againſt them with twenty thouſand, whether poor
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100734:5"/>Duſt and Aſhes were able to cope with Omnipotence, the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> with the Ancient of Days; and if not while he was yet a great way off, before he came nigh to them in Judgment and Fury, to ſend an Embaſſie and deſire conditions of Peace, to ſend thoſe prevalent Ambaſſadors, penitential Tears and Prayers, which never fail of ſucceſs at the Court of Heaven, and ſo the <hi>Septu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agint</hi> Tranſlates the Phraſe, prepare to call upon the Lord thy God, and agreeably St. <hi>Hierome</hi> and others under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it. And to me the ſoftneſs of the Expreſſion ſeems to favour this Interpretation, wherein he ſtiles himſelf <hi>Their God,</hi> prepare to meet <hi>Thy God,</hi> intimating to them, that however they by their heinous Provocations had juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forfeited it; yet he was unwilling that that Covenant-Relation between them, whereby he was to be their God, and they his People, ſhould be diſſolved. They were indeed a ſinful People, but yet he was ſtill ready to own himſelf <hi>Their God,</hi> thereby encouraging them to make their Applications to him.</p>
            <p>The Meaning then of the whole Verſe may be this, becauſe thou haſt been proof againſt thoſe Judgments which I have in Mercy inflicted upon thee for thy Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, I am now reſolved to pour out thoſe upon thee which ſhall be for thy utter Ruin and Exciſion, unleſs thou makeſt uſe of that one opportunity which is yet left, which thy Long-Suffering God now tenders to thee; (and O that thou wouldeſt embrace it!) of Returning and Reconciling thy ſelf to me by true and ſincere Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. <hi>Therefore Thus will I do unto thee, O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words thus explained we have three things Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable.
<list>
                  <item>1. A dreadful Judgment denounced againſt <hi>Iſrael, Thus will I do unto thee.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100734:5"/>
                  <item>2. The provoking cauſe thereof implyed in the word <hi>Therefore (viz.)</hi> their incorrigibleneſs under former Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, becauſe I have puniſhed you, and yet ye have not returned, <hi>Therefore.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Laſtly, here is a gracious way pointed out for their Eſcape, <hi>Prepare to meet thy God, O</hi> Iſrael.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall Treat of the firſt and ſecond together, and from the Judgment denounced, with the provoking cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, obſerve to you this Poſition,</p>
            <p>That when God's Judgments, upon a People or Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, fail of their deſigned ends, which are to lead them to Repentance, when they are not Reformed, or made Better, but rather the Worſe by them, the State of that People is deſperate, they are nigh unto Exciſion.</p>
            <p>Which Propoſition, when I ſhall have briefly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirmed, I will by way of Application enquire whether God has not uſed theſe Methods to reclaim us of this Nation, and what Effects his Judgments have had upon us: and if it ſhall appear that notwithſtanding he has Exerciſed us with thoſe Diſpenſations, yet we have not returned unto him, but gone on incorrigibly in our ſins. I ſuppoſe I may with good Reaſon in the laſt place endeavour to perſuade you to prepare to meet your God by a ſpeedy and thorough Repentance, that ſo we may avert thoſe ſeverer Retributions that hang over our Heads, and eſcape that ruin, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we muſt expect to be unavoidably involved in, which is the great Buſineſs and Deſign of the Day.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100734:6"/> 1. I am to ſhew that when God's Judgments, upon a People or Nation, fail of their deſigned ends, which are to lead them to Repentance, when they are not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, or made Better, but rather the Worſe by them, the State of that People is deſperate, they are nigh unto Exciſion.</p>
            <p>Now that God's deſign in inflicting Judgments upon a People is to bring them to Repentance, which is implyed in the Propoſition, is very evident from Scripture, <hi>Iſa.</hi> i. After God had complained of his People <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that tho he had nouriſhed and brought them up, uſed all Methods to inſtitute and keep them in his Ways and Service, yet they were a rebellious and ſinful Nation, a People laden with iniquity: he adds, <hi>Why ſhould ye be ſtricken, ye will revolt more and more?</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, to what end ſhould I beſtow my Corrections and Chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon you? I find they do but make you revolt more, and go the further backward from me; and they are but thrown away upon you if they have no better Effects; my ends in them are to reduce you when you are going aſtray, to prevent your future Deviations from me, and if they obtain not theſe Purpoſes, to what end ſhould I Exerciſe you with them? If ye only revolt more, why ſhould ye be ſtricken any more? 'Tis not the deſign of my ſtriking to drive you farther from me, but to bring you nearer to me. Nay, In <hi>Jer.</hi> iii. God makes thoſe Puniſhments, which he had inflicted upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> an aggravation of <hi>Judahs</hi> Crime, that ſhe did not return unto him, <hi>Though I put away,</hi> ſays he, <hi>backsliding</hi> Iſrael <hi>for her adulteries, and gave her a bill of divorce, yet her treacherous ſiſter</hi> Judah <hi>feared not, but played the harlot alſo, and returned not unto me.</hi> Verſe 8. But now why ſhould God make thoſe Judgments, which he had laid
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100734:6"/>upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> an Aggravation of <hi>Judah's</hi> Crime in not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting, and a ground of his ſeverer Anger againſt her, if the deſign and tendency of his Judgments had not been to Reform not only thoſe that ſmart under them, but even all thoſe alſo to whom any notice of them ſhould come? And to name no more places, the Apoſtle puts the thing out of all doubt, <hi>Heb.</hi> xii. 10. <hi>The fathers of our fleſh chaſten us for their own pleaſure,</hi> to gratifie it may be an angry Paſſion; but he the Father of Spirits, God chaſtens us <hi>for our profit, that we may be partakers of his holineſs.</hi> This is the end of his Chaſtiſements and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to work Goodneſs and Vertue in us, to make us partakers of Holineſs.</p>
            <p>And 'tis evident that Puniſhments have a natural ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to theſe ends. Nothing more apt to make us out of love with our ſins than the ſmarting a little for them; the taſting of the bitterneſs that is hid under theſe gilded Pills, if any thing, will make us diſreliſh and nauſeate them; when we feel nothing but the pleaſure of the ſin we are enamoured with it, and greedily purſue it; but when we are ſenſible of the ſmart and miſery that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it, then we begin to abate of our love and value for it. A long Series of Impunity and Proſperity is apt to make a People wax Fat and forget God, but in their Afflictions they will ſeek him early or diligently, as the Prophet ſpeaks. When therefore he ſees a Nation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volting from him, committing Whoredoms againſt him, proſtituting themſelves to their Luſts, forſaking him and cleaving to their Vices, then he lays his Rod upon them to convince them how bitter and grievous a thing it is to depart from the living God; then he throws in a daſh of Gall of Wormwood to embitter thoſe ſatifactions and delights to them, which they are ſo in love with.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100734:7"/>
            <p> Which as it is a very great demonſtration of the goodneſs of our Heavenly Father, when the very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereſt of his Diſpenſations to the Sons of Men are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of his Mercy to them, his very Judgments tokens of his Paternal Love, and the deſigned ends of his Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Corrections, the Good and Reformation of his People, ſo muſt it mightily inhance the guilt of thoſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that are not wrought upon by ſuch gracious and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacious Methods.</p>
            <p>Chiefly becauſe theſe are commonly the laſt remedies that God tries to reduce them, he does not ordinarily uſe theſe till he finds ſofter Methods ineffectual, and if theſe work not with a People, but they are proof againſt them alſo, what will become of them? When a Phiſician has Cupt and Scarified, and uſed his laſt methods upon a Patient, if they have no Effects he gives him over, if he continues ſtupid and inſenſible under thoſe Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it is a ſign he is near his end.</p>
            <p>Beloved, God Almighty does not ſtrike or inflict Puniſhments, till he finds he cannot win us by fair means; Puniſhing is his ſtrange Work, he afflicts not willingly, nor grieves the Children of Men; he had rather allure us by Kindneſs, draw us with the Cords of a Man, with the Bands of Love: but when he finds that his gentler dealings will not reduce us, that we are made looſe and diſſolute by kindneſs, emboldened and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged in our ſins by his forbearance, then he uſes his ſeverer Diſpenſations, then he laſhes and ſtrikes us, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits our Iniquities upon us, to make us in ſome meaſure feel the dreadful Conſequences of them; but if this will not do, this his laſt method cannot affect or amend us, there remain no more for us.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100734:8"/>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:100734:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And when once a Nation has overcome all God's Arts of preſerving them, and made themſelves ripe for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, Execution will quickly follow.</p>
            <p>For it is not with a Nation as with a particular Perſon; a particular Perſon may have filled up the meaſure of his ſins, made himſelf ripe for Ruin, and yet his Puniſhment may be deferred, it may be not Executed all his Life; yea poſſibly he may enjoy the affluence of all good things. The Scriptures frequently ſpeak of the flouriſhing condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of particular wicked Men, and their exemption from thoſe Plagues and Miſeries, which others better than themſelves are ſubject to, and labour under; their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities may have been full, and yet no preſent Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment awarded out againſt them: but as to Kingdoms and Nations God's Procedure is quite different, when the ſins of a Nation are full, preſent Execution ſucceeds, as is plain from the Hiſtory of God's dealing, whether with his own People or with other Nations.</p>
            <p>And there is this Reaſon for this difference in God's Procedure; particular Perſons are capable of Retributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in another Life after this, there is a time coming when they may be called to account, and ſufficiently puniſhed for their ſins; though their Iniquities are not viſited here, though they do not ſmart under God's Judgments in this Life, but ſeem rather to inherit the Favours of Heaven, yet as long as there is a Day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed; a day of deſtruction which they are reſerved to, wherein their ſhort lived Impunity, it may be Jollity here, ſhall be turned into an eternity of Tribulation, and Anguiſh, and Pain; this may be without any impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God's Holineſs, Truth, or Juſtice.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:100734:9"/>
            <p> But for Nations or Kingdoms it is otherwiſe, for a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Kingdom, conſidered as ſuch, is not capable of any Retributions in a Life after this; for in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurection we ſhall not be conſidered as Perſons em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodyed in ſuch or ſuch a Community: In the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there is no Marrying, or giving in Marriage ſays our Saviour: In the other World we ſhall not live in thoſe Capacities we do here, all Relations that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us now will then ceaſe; all ſuch as Husband and Wife, Prince and People, King and Subject, be quite ſwallowed up in that World: And therefore ſince the Relations and Societies of this World ſhall then be Diſſolved; it is clear that a Nation, as a Nation, cannot receive any Retributions in another Life after this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then it will ceaſe to be a Nation, and cannot there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be Rewarded or Puniſhed as ſuch; from whence it is certain that every Nation ſhall meet with the preſent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns of their wickedneſs here, becauſe God will be ſure to ſhew himſelf as Juſt in his Dealings with Nations as with particular Perſons, and that he can no more paſs by the ſins of one than of the other.</p>
            <p>From all which we may conclude, that when a People or Nation have reſiſted all God's endeavours for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, the ſtrivings of his Mercies, and the efforts of his Judgments, too; will neither hearken to the ſtill Voice of his Kindneſs, nor the louder Voice of his Rod; are not only made bold and ſecure by his forbearance, but hardned in the fire of Affliction; when they defie all his Arts for their amendment, and have no impreſſions made upon them by his utmoſt, laſt, moſt effectual Method; the ſtate ſurely of that Nation is deſperate, and the day of their Ruin and utter Exciſion not far off.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:100734:9"/>
            <p> To apply then what has been ſaid to our ſelves: Let us, I beſeech you, take an impartial view of our ſelves, and of God's Diſpenſations towards us of this Nation; let us examine whether he has not been uſing the ſame Methods to reclaim us that he Exerciſed <hi>Iſrael</hi> with, and what Effects they have had upon us.</p>
            <p>I need not go ſo far back as to the Ages of our Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, I need only refreſh your Memories, and put you in mind of various Judgments that God has poured out upon this Kingdom in your own time, even the very ſame that he here in the Text threatens <hi>Iſrael</hi> for their incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigibleneſs under.</p>
            <p>For has he not overthrown ſome of us as well as them, as he did <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> conſumed not only the greateſt part of the Metropolis of our Land with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Fire, and made it a heap of Rubbiſh and Aſhes, but many other of our leſſer Towns, as the frequent Briefs, of late years eſpecially, inform us, and ſome of them with Fire immediately from Heaven?</p>
            <p>Has he not alſo ſent the Peſtilence among us after the manner of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> viſited this Land with a ſweeping Plague that carried away many thouſands to their long Home?</p>
            <p>Have not our young Men too been ſlain with the Sword, have we not been engaged in Wars at Home and Abroad? and all thoſe three of his ſore Judgments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen us within the memory of moſt of us?</p>
            <p>And as for the fourth, which the Prophet mentions, that of cleanneſs Teeth, though, bleſſed be his name, we
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100734:10"/>have not lately laboured under a Famine of our dayly Bread for the ſupport of our Natural Lives; yet, Has he not been lately threatning us with a far ſeverer Famine, a Famine of the Word of God? and Man ſhall not live by Bread only, but by every Word that proceedeth out of the Mouth of God. Were we not apprehenſive not long ſince, and had we not too good Grounds for it, that he was going to remove our Candleſtick, to deprive us of that pure Religion, and excellent way of Worſhip we are bleſſed with, and to give us up to Popiſh Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and Idolatry, into the Hands of thoſe Men that would have taken from us the ſincere Milk of the Word, that Food which God has afforded us for the nouriſhment of our Souls to Eternal Life, and would have ſtarved us with lying Legends inſtead thereof?</p>
            <p>Were not the Emiſaries of <hi>Rome,</hi> the implacable Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our Church and Religion, labouring with all their might: and induſtriouſly improving the favourable opportunities, they injoyed under the laſt Reign, to deſtroy ours and eſtabliſh their own Religion? and were they not too likely in all human appearance to have been too ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesful? Had they not made a very large Progreſs for ſo ſhort a time? Did not their Prieſts appear every where barefaced in deſpight of our Laws? Did they not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their Abominations, celebrate their Idolatrous Services in the moſt publick and conſpicuous places in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom? Had they not built many Altars and High Places for that purpoſe? Had they not ſeized ſome of our Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries, part of our Univerſities, to breed up a Succeſſion of diſciplined and inſtructed perſons to carry on and finiſh the Work they had begun? Did they not openly ſolicit all they had opportunity or hopes of Perverting, uſing all Methods, offering Rewards and Preferments to ſome, threatning, menacing others to make them comply
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100734:10"/>with them: in a word, Did they not look upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as ſecure of gaining their Point? And had they not all the Reaſon to hope, as we to fear, that they ſhould have triumphed in the ruins of this Church and Religion, that either a furious Zeal for their Cauſe, an irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Hatred to us, a Serpentine Subtilty, indefatigable Induſtry, the favour of the Government, the Laws as they were managed, the Army, almoſt all Offices Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary and Civil in their Hands, and the aſſured expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Foreign Aſſiſtance could afford them? And if we ſeem now in ſome meaſure to be delivered from theſe deſigns of theirs, if God ſeem now to have removed this Judgment, yet believe me, if we anſwer not his ends and deſigns in Threatning us with it, the preſent ſuſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it will not prove a total removal, but only a lightning before death, a puting back of his Arm to ſtrike with a greater force.</p>
            <p>Nay, Is not God at this time making bare his Arm a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us? Are we not unavoidably ingaged in a War with a neighbouring and very potent Prince? and May we not expect all the Hoſtilities and Injuries that his equal Hatred to our Nation and Religion, his Politick Counſellors, the Wealth of his whole Kingdom, or his numerous Forces can ſuggeſt to, or enable him to put in Execution?</p>
            <p>And which is yet a more ſad conſideration? Has not God ſent a Spirit of Faction and Diviſion among us? Are we not unreaſonably diſunited among our ſelves, broken and crumbled into Sects and Parties, regardleſs of the Common Enemy, and only jealous of, and watchful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one another? And can a Kingdom ſo divided againſt it ſelf long ſtand?</p>
            <p>Thus, my Brethren, has God been Manuring and Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivating this Land of ours, with various Chaſtiſements
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100734:11"/>and Corrections, to try if he could make it bring forth the <hi>Peaceable Fruits of Righteouſneſs:</hi> when he found that though <hi>favour were ſhewn to us we would not learn righteouſneſs,</hi> he ſent his Judgments, his laſt reſerve, to try if they could teach our Inhabitants that Leſſon.</p>
            <p>And what effects have his Judgments had upon us? Have we hearkned unto the Voice of his Rod, and anſwered the ends of his Corrections? Has the Fire of Affliction refined and purged us from our Droſs and Corruption? Have his Severities mortified our Sins and Vices? Has the Lance let out the impoſthumated Putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction? Has his viſiting our Iniquities upon us made us out of love with them, and his Terrors perſuaded us to forſake them? Have we been more fearful to offend him, more careful to pleaſe him, more awfully regardful of his Majeſty, more Zealous for his Honor, more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and conſtant in our attendance upon his Service and our Duty?</p>
            <p>'Tis certainly no time to diſſemble with God, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon our ſelves, the Day calls for ſincerity and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiality in our examinations: and, if we will ſpeak the truth, Have we not been proof againſt theſe Methods of Gods too, and as we have abuſed his Mercy, and deſpiſed his Goodneſs, ſo defied his Judgments alſo?</p>
            <p>For does there not every where appear barefaced the ſame daring Impiety againſt God, the ſame Atheiſtical Scoffing at Religion, the ſame Neglect and Contempt of his Worſhip, the ſame Profanation of his Word by drolling upon it, and lightly uſing it in common Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; the ſame Profanation of his Name by horrid Oaths, Curſes, and Imprecations; the ſame Profanation of his Day by converting it to Secular uſes, ſpending it
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100734:11"/>in worldly Buſineſs, idle Paſtimes, and vicious Practices; the ſame Profanation of his Houſe by wilfully abſtaining from it, or coldly, formally, or irreverently behaving our ſelves at it? Does there not appear the ſame inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and uncharitableneſs to our Neighbours, the ſame Circumvention and Defraudation in Bargaining, the ſame falſe Weights and Meaſures in Buying and Selling, the ſame Extortion, Oppreſſion, and Deceit in all Dealings, the ſame uncharitable Cenſuring, Backbiting and Detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? Does there not appear the ſame Intemperance and Incontinence againſt our ſelves, the ſame Revelling and Drunkeneſs, the ſame Chambering and Wantonneſs? In a word, Is there not the ſame general Diſſolution of Manners, the ſame unreſtrained Practice of Wickedneſs of all ſorts and degrees, as there was before God made uſe of thoſe his Judgments, which I have enumerated, to Reclaim and Reform us?</p>
            <p>Nay, Are we not by inſenſible degrees arrived to a ſtrange impudence in ſinning, not known to former Ages? Men were content formerly to ſin ſecretly, would look out for the moſt private places and cloſeſt Retirements to perpetrate their Villanies in: Time was when the Fool could think it enough to ſay in his Heart there is no God, when the Adulterer would watch for the twilight, that the darkneſs might cover his foul Embraces, when thoſe that were Drunk would be Drunk in the Night, that the Sun and Men might not be Witneſſes of their worſe than brutal Practices: Sinners were then ſo modeſt that they would bluſh upon a Diſcovery:</p>
            <p>But now Men have worn off all that ſilly baſhfulneſs, are ſo far from ſeeking privacies to commit, or excuſes to palliate their Sins, that they publiſh them as <hi>Sodom,</hi> and glory in their ſhame. The Streets the moſt conſpicuous
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100734:12"/>places are conſcious to the moſt daring Blaſphemies, the moſt provoking Oaths and Curſes, the moſt beaſtly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperances and Uncleanneſſes, the moſt crying Murders; nay theſe are things which Men value themſelves upon, take a pride in recounting how many Men they have Murdered with the Sword, or with the Bottle, how many Women they have abuſed and ruined, how many Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites they have made to Atheiſm, and how effectually cleared themſelves from all ſuſpition of Vertue and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity.</p>
            <p>And then if this be our caſe, if God has ſmitten us and we remain incorrigible, and all his Diſcipline has only ſerved to advance us to a greater proficiency in the Devils School, if he has uſed the ſame Methods to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce us that he did to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and we give him the ſame Reaſon that they did to complain, that yet we have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned unto him; what can we expect but that he ſhould threaten us as he did them in the Text, that <hi>Therefore thus he will do unto us,</hi> pour out upon us Vials of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer Judgments then we have yet felt, even till he has made a full end of us?</p>
            <p>And <hi>what ſhall we do,</hi> as the Prophet asks, <hi>in the day of viſitation, and in the deſolation that ſhall come from far, and to whom ſhall we fly for help?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why, Behold God has anſwered the Prophets queſtion in the latter part of the Text, <hi>Prepare to meet thy God O</hi> Iſrael, endeavour to appeaſe him as <hi>Jacob</hi> did his angry Brother <hi>Eſau</hi> by ſending a Preſent before him, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure he will accept of us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But wherewithal ſhall we come before the Lord, and bow our ſelves before the high God? ſhall we come with burnt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, with calves of a year old?</hi>
            </p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:100734:13"/>
            <p> Shall I tell you that this is it which Authority is this day calling you to? The meaning and deſign of this Monthly Faſt enjoyned by their Majeſties, as I obſerved in the beginning, is not that you ſhould only deprive your Stomachs of a Meals Meat, much leſs that you ſhould <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pare from your Tables to conſume upon your Luſts, leaſt of all that ſhould abſtain from your Food and Vices one day, that you may return to both with the greater Appetite the next; <hi>Not that you ſhould hang down your heads like bullruſhes, and ſpread ſackcloth and aſhes,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaks, not that you ſhould only put on a dejected Countenance, and ſome outward ſhews of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, but that you ſhould humble your ſouls for your ſins, that <hi>You ſhould looſe the bands of wickedneſs, undo the heavy burdens, and break every yoke; that you ſhould waſh and make clean, put away the evil of your doings from before the eyes of the Lord, and turn to him with full pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This deſign of working a general Reformation in their Subjects their Majeſties have been endeavouring to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh, not only by appointing ſuch frequent days of Humiliation, but by Letters and Orders of Council di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the Subordinate Magiſtrates, and to the Clergy, whereby we are obliged to Read in our Churches, and the Magiſtrates to put in Execution our wholeſome Laws againſt thoſe Peſts and Troublers of our <hi>Iſrael;</hi> our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Drunkards, Swearers, and Sabbath-Breakers: And let me beſeech thoſe of you to whom the Execution of Juſtice is committed, by the Bowels and Mercies of God that you be Zealous and Impartial in Animadverting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch ſcandalous Offenders, that ſo thoſe Wretches, whom the future and unſeen Retributions of another World can make no Impreſſions upon, may be deterred
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100734:13"/>by the inflictions of the Penalties of the Laws from their bold and fearleſs Commiſſion of thoſe crying Sins, which are ſo reproachful to our Holy Profeſſion, ſo provoking in the Eyes of God, and of ſuch dangerous Conſequence to our Church and Nation.</p>
            <p>Shall I to this add, what the laſt words ſuggeſt to me, that this is it which the ſaid deplorable Eſtate of our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided Church and Nation calls you to, whoſe Fall and Ruin muſt unavoidably attend your refuſing to anſwer theſe Calls: And were you but affected as Holy Men of old have been, as <hi>Jeremy</hi> who wiſhed <hi>his head waters, and his eyes a fountain of tears that he might weep for the ſlain of the danghter of his people,</hi> or as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> who wept bitterly, and would not be comforted becauſe of the ſpoiling of the Daughter of his People; had you but the ſame Affection to our <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> did you wiſh as well to our <hi>Sion</hi> as they did to theirs, you would give Ear to her pitiful Cry, compaſſionate her lamentable Condition, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by your Repentance to raiſe her up, and prevent her ruin. And what ſhall I ſay more to preſs you to it, what Motives can I add to theſe I have now ſuggeſted? If neither the Pathetical beſeeching of your Native King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Reformed Church, in whoſe Wellfare or Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry every one of us muſt more or leſs ſhare; nor the Pious Injunctions of your Governors, whoſe Juſt and Righteous Commands ought to be of weight with you; nor the more forcible Call of God himſelf, who will be ſure ſeverely to revenge the Affront you will offer by turning the Deaf Ear to him: If none of theſe can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with you, neither love to your Selves and Country, reſpect to your Sovereigns, nor fear of God work with you; what Arguments can be effectual? If you will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hearken to the loud importunate Call of God nor Man in a matter of ſuch vaſt importance to your ſelves, it is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100734:14"/>to be feared, you will never hearken to any thing till you hear God ſay depart ye Curſed.</p>
            <p>But, My Brethren, give me leave to hope better things concerning you, and things that make for Peace, that you will at laſt hearken to, and obey theſe earneſt and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate Solicitations, that you will break off your ſins by <hi>Repentance, and caſt away your tranſgreſſions, whereby you have tranſgreſſed, and become new creatures, that iniquity may not be our ruin;</hi> that you will each and every of you ſet about Reforming and Amending one; and this day reſolve and enter upon a courſe of Penitence and New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Life, that ſo God may be intreated for the Land.</p>
            <p>But ſome one may object, of what great concern to the Nation can my ſingle Repentance or Impenitence be? I am but one, and ſurely cannot by one or the other much forward or hinder the Kingdoms either wellfare or ruin: There are enow beſides to do the Work without me, I may enjoy my Luſts and Vices, and let others Repent for the Nation.</p>
            <p>But 1. What if all, and every one in the Nation, ſhould think and do the ſame, would not the Work be well done then? And all have juſt the ſame Reaſon, <hi>i. e.</hi> none at all, For</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſins of every ſingle Perſon, and thine in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular have added to, and made up that Meaſure of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, which has angred God, and provoked him to ſhake his Rod over the Kingdom, and therefore it is but Reaſon and Juſtice that ſince thou haſt contributed to that Maſs and Weight which is ready to ſink the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom into ruin, thou ſhouldeſt bear thy part in taking off the Load. Beſides,</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:100734:14"/> 3. How knoweſt thou but thy ſingle Repentance may Save, or at leaſt Reprieve the Nation? Time was when ten Righteous Men, if ſo many could have been found in <hi>Sodom,</hi> would have preſerved that place; and how canſt thou tell but by thy ſincere Converſion thou maiſt make up that number for whoſe ſakes God will ſpare this Land? And would it not be matter of Melancholy Reflection to thee, if for want of thee ſuch a number ſhould not be found for which God would ſpare it? But</p>
            <p n="4">4. Should there be enough without thee to do the Work, ſhould God for the ſake of others of his Servants, that cry day and night to him, ſpare us, and turn our days of Humiliation into days of Thankſgiving, yet what right canſt thou pretend to any ſhare in the Mercy? Thou that refuſeſt to hearken to the Words of Gods Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, how canſt thou expect any other Fate than that of the incredulous Lord, that disbelieved <hi>Eliſha</hi>'s Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of Plenty, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> vii. That with thine Eyes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly thou maiſt ſee, but ſhall not partake of the bleſſing. Whereas,</p>
            <p>Laſtly, If thy Repentance ſhould prove unſucceſsful for the Kingdom, if the Sins thereof ſhould be ſo Ripe, their Iniquities ſo Full that God will not ſpare it, yet aſſuredly thou ſhalt deliver thine own Soul, ſo the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God aſſures thee <hi>Ezek</hi> xiv. <hi>That when a land has ſinned ſo grievouſly againſt God that his hand is ſtretched out, and he will not accept of the faſting tears and prayers of</hi> Noah, Daniel, <hi>and</hi> Job, <hi>for the deliverance of the land, yet they ſhall deliver their own ſouls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Away then with ſuch idle put offs, let us not ſhift off this neceſſary duty from one to another, but
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100734:15"/>having ſuch invitations and ſuch encouragements, let every of us ſet to our Parts, and contribute each ones Tears, Prayers, and Repentance to the Reverſing the Decree that is gone forth againſt us: ſo let us prepare to meet our God who is ſtill ready to own that Relation; yea deſirous to Repent him of the evil that he thought to do unto us, and to make our <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> yet a praiſe upon the whole Earth.</p>
            <p>Where then are the Penitent <hi>Davids</hi> and <hi>Jeremy</hi>'s, that may weep Tears for the ſins of a Nation to waſh away the guilt thereof? Where are the Meek <hi>Moſes</hi>'s, the choſen ones of God, that may ſtand in the Gap, and turn away his wrath that he deſtroy us not? Where are the faithful <hi>Abrahams,</hi> the Friends of God, that may intercede powerfully, and ſucceſsfully for a ſinful and diſobedient People? Yea, where are the ten Righteous for whoſe ſakes God will ſpare the Place? Would it not, my Brethren, be a glorious thing for you and me to make a part of that number for whoſe ſakes God would ſpare this Nation, to be the Saviours of the Kingdom? Why ſuch are all the truly Contrite and Penitent Souls in the Land.</p>
            <p>O then let us favour the Stones of <hi>Sion,</hi> let it pity us to ſee her in the Duſt, let us pray for the Peace of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and let us live and Repent for it too; and then we ſhall not need to fear all the Enemies of our <hi>Sion,</hi> for God will be for us, and if he be for us who can be againſt us? Then let the Children of <hi>Ammon,</hi> and <hi>Moab,</hi> and Mount <hi>Seir,</hi> the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> with them that dwell at <hi>Tyre,</hi> come forth to Battle againſt us, they ſhall not be able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail over us, for there will be many with us: Then we may bid defiance to all the Power and Policy of <hi>France,</hi> and treachery of home-bred Enemies, for our God will be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100734:15"/>our Guide and Protector, our Shield and Buckler, will ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us from Foreign and Domeſtick Adverſaries, yea, will bleſs us in making a viſible return of Mercy upon us, will cauſe our Nation to Flouriſh, and be the Admiration and Envy of its Neighbours, will continue to us our excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently Conſtituted Government, and preſerve our Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Apoſtolical Church, that neither the deſigns of thoſe who would betray us into Slavery or Anarchy ſhall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the Subverſion of one, nor the Gates of Hell or <hi>Rome</hi> prevail againſt the other. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
